"Are Baruka Nuts
the Healthiest Nut?"
There is a new nut on the
market called baru almonds
branded as “barukas,” or just baru nuts.
Technically, it isn’t a nut but a seed
that's native to the Brazilian Savannah,
known as the Cerrado, which
is sadly now among the most
threatened ecosystems in the world.
Over the last 30 years, extensive cattle
ranching and feed crop production
to fatten said cattle have
destroyed much of this ecosystem.
So, hey, if we can make it profitable
not to cut down the native trees
by selling baru nuts, for example,
then that could be good
for the ecosystem’s health.
But what about our health?
Although baru nuts are
popular and widely consumed,
few studies report on
their biological properties.
They do have a lot of
polyphenol phytonutrients,
presumably accounting for
their high antioxidant activity,
and 90%of the phytonutrients
are present in the peel.
So, are they nutritious? Sure.
But do they have any
special health benefits
(and not just for the
treatment of chubby mice)?
Groups fed baru nuts showed lower
cholesterol, supposedly indicating
that they have a great
potential for dietary use in
preventing and controlling
cholesterol problems.
But their groups were rats,
and that was compared to lard.
Basically anything lowers your
cholesterol compared to eating lard.
Nevertheless, there haven’t been
any reports about the effect
of baru almonds consumption on
human health, until this study.
A randomized, controlled study
of humans found that eating less
than an ounce a day for six weeks
led to a 9% drop in LDL cholesterol.
Twenty grams would be
about 15 nuts or a palmful.
Like many other nut studies,
even though the research subjects
were told to add nuts to their regular
diets, there was no weight gain,
presumably because nuts are
so filling, you inadvertently
cut down on other foods
throughout the day.
How good is a 9.4% drop in LDL?
Well, that’s the kind of drop
you can get from regular almonds,
though macadamias and pistachios
may work even better,
but those were at much higher doses.
So, it appeared that 20 grams
of baru nuts worked as well as
73 grams of almonds, and so
on a per serving basis,
or a per calorie basis, baru nuts
really did seem to be special.
Now there are lower
dose nut studies showing
similar or even better results.
Here people were given 25 grams
of almonds for just four weeks
and got about a 6% drop.
And in this study, people were given
just 10 grams of almonds a day,
I mean we’re talkin’ just seven
individual almonds a day,
and got more like a 30% drop in
the same time frame as the baru nuts.
Three times better at half
the dose with regular almonds.
The biggest reason we’re
more confident in regular almonds
is that studies have
been done over and over,
more than a dozen
randomized controlled trials,
whereas in the only other
cholesterol trial of baru nuts
there was no significant benefit
at all for LDL cholesterol,
even at the same 20-gram
dose given for even longer—
a period of eight weeks.
That’s a bummer.
The primary reason I would
suggest choosing other nuts instead,
though, is that you
can’t get baru nuts raw.
They contain certain compounds
that have to be inactivated by heat
before human consumption.
So, the reason raw nuts are
preferable is because of advanced
glycation end products (AGEs),
so-called glycotoxins,
which are known to
contribute to increased
oxidative stress and inflammation.
Glycotoxins are naturally present
in uncooked animal-derived foods,
but then dry-heat cooking like
grilling can make things worse.
The three highest levels recorded
are bacon, broiled hot dogs,
and roasted barbequed chicken skin
(nothing comes close to that.)
Chicken McNuggets come in here,
but, anyway, any foods high in fat
and protein can create AGEs
at high enough temperatures.
So, although plant foods tend
to contain relatively few AGEs,
even after cooking, there are some
high-fat, high-protein plant foods.
For example, boiled tofu,
like in a soup, is down here,
but the same serving size
of broiled tofu is up here.
Now again, with most plant foods
it’s not at all a problem.
Like here’s a raw apple,
and here’s a baked apple.
It doesn’t really matter since
it’s not high fat or high protein.
I was surprised that
veggie burgers were so low,
even when baked or fried.
But nuts and seeds are up in tofu
territory, especially when roasted,
which is why I would
recommend raw nuts and seeds
and nut and seed butters
whenever you have a choice.